A Finding Aid to the Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney Papers, 1851-1975, bulk 1888-1942, in the Archives of American Art AAA.whitgert
Archives of American Art
- Printed Material, 1859-1942; Series 9; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 27-28, 36
  - Oversize, Clippings scanned with Box 27, Folder 18, 1891-1899 (Box 36)
  - Oversize, Clippings of Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture scanned with Box 28, Folder 2, undated (Box 36)
  - Oversize, Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements - Other Artists scanned with Box 28, Folder 7, 1910-1932 (Box 36)
  - Oversize, Miscellaneous scanned with Box 28, Folder 8, 1916-1925 (Box 36)
- Photographs, 1862-1942; Series 10; 6.4 Linear feet Boxes 28-32, 36-41, OVs 43-51
  This series consists primarily of photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, her studios (in Old Westbury and Paris), her exhibitions and exhibitions at her studio, and her sculpture, and photographs of the Vanderbilt and Whitney families and residences.
  Photographs are arranged as six subseries.
  10.1: Photographs of Family, 1862-1931
  10.2: Photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1880s-1941
  10.3: Photographs of Residences and Studios, 1896-1935
  10.4: Photographs of Exhibitions, 1910s-1942
  10.5: Photographs of Sculpture, 1904-1935
  10.6: Other Photographs, 1895-1915
  Photographs have been scanned in entirety with the exception of duplicates, photographs with permission restrictions, blank versos of photographs, and negatives.
  - Photographs of Family, 1862-1931; 10.1
    This subseries consists of early photographs of the Vanderbilt and Whitney families, and photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's own family, including her husband, Harry Payne Whitney, her children, Flora, Cornelius, and Barbara, and other family members. Early photographs of the Vanderbilt family include ones of Whitney's grandfather, "Commodore" Cornelius Vanderbilt, and her father, Cornelius Vanderbilt II, and one from the Vanderbilt family trip to Florida in 1896. Early photographs of the Whitney family include ones of William C. Whitney and Flora Payne Whitney (Whitney's in-laws), ones of Pauline and Harry Payne Whitney as children, and ones of other family, friends, and business and political associates of William C. Whitney. Photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's own family include ones from her honeymoon, ones of her children and ones of her with her children (including one of Whitney with her mother, daughter, and grandchild, representing four generations of the family), and ones from various family weddings. Also found are photographs of Whitney's childhood friend, Esther Hunt.
    Photographs have been scanned in entirety with the exception of duplicates, photographs with permission restrictions, and blank versos of photographs.
    Family photographs are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - "Commodore" Cornelius Vanderbilt (grandfather), undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Cornelius Vanderbilt II (father), circa 1896 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Reproduction of Portrait of Cornelius Vanderbilt II, undated (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - William C. Whitney (father-in-law), circa 1860s-1900s (Box 28, Folder 16-18)
    - Whitney Family, 1862-1889; undated (Box 28, Folder 19-20)
    - Flora Payne Whitney (mother-in-law) and Senator Henry B. Payne, before 1896 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Pauline and Harry Payne Whitney and Other Family, 1892; undated (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - Whitney Family and Friends, circa 1890s (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Whitney Family (?), undated (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Business and Political Associates of William C. Whitney, circa 1890s (Box 28, Folder 25)
    - William C. Whitney with Family and Friends, circa 1900 (Box 28, Folder 26)
    - Harry Payne Whitney (Box 28)
      - As a Boy, circa 1880s (Box 28, Folder 27-28)
      - As a Young Man, circa 1890s (Box 28, Folder 29)
      - As an Adult, 1900-1917 (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
      - Polo, 1914 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Esther Hunter (friend), 1880s?; 1894 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Vanderbilt Trip to Florida (with Harry Payne Whitney), 1896 March (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Gertrude and Harry Payne Whitney on Their Honeymoon, 1896 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Gertrude and Harry Payne Whitney with Children (Flora and Barbara), 1897; 1903 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Gladys Vanderbilt's (sister) Wedding, 1908 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Friends and Family, 1900s-1910s (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Flora, Cornelius, and Barbara Whitney (children), 1900s-1910s (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney with Mother, Daughter, and Grandchild, circa 1922 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Olive Paget's Wedding, 1919 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Flora Whitney's Wedding, 1920 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Barbara Whitney's Wedding, 1924 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Gloria Vanderbilt (niece), 1924-1939 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Cornelius Whitney's Wedding (?), 1931 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 29, Folder 17-18)
    - Oversize, Reproduction of Portrait of Cornelius Vanderbilt II scanned with Box 28, Folder 15, undated (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Vanderbilt Trip to Florida (with Harry Payne Whitney) scanned with Box 29, Folder 5, 1896 March (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Gertrude and Harry Payne Whitney with Children (Flora and Barbara) scanned with Box 29, Folder 7, 1903; 1897 (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Flora, Cornelius, and Barbara Whitney (children) scanned with Box 29, Folder 10, 1900s-1910s (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney with Mother, Daughter, and Grandchild scanned with Box 29, Folder 11, circa 1922 (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Olive Paget's (niece) Wedding scanned with Box 29, Folder 12, 1919 (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Flora Whitney's Wedding scanned with Box 29, Folder 13, 1920 (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Cornelius Whitney's Wedding (?) scanned with Box 29, Folder 16, 1931 (Box 36)
    - Oversize, Unidentified, undated (Box 36)
  - Photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1880s-1941; 10.2
    This subseries consists of portraits and photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney. Portraits include early ones of Whitney as young girl and young woman, later ones taken by noted photographers Amemiya, Baron Adolf de Meyer and Count Jean de Strelecki, and proofs of ones taken by Edward Steichen, among others. Photographs include ones in costume, campaigning for the presidential candidate, Charles Hughes, in 1916, traveling, receiving an honorary degree from New York University in 1922, with Dr. Boliario Porras presumably conferring about the Panama-Roosevelt Memorial, at the opening of the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1931 (including some photographs of the museum taken by the photographer Berenice Abbott), and various ones with her husband, friends, and other family.
    Photographs of Whitney can also be found amongst the sculpture photographs.
    Photographs in this subseries are arranged in rough chronological order. Reproductions of painted portraits of Whitney, scattered photographs of friends, colleagues, and suitors, and negatives are arranged in files at the end of the subseries.
    - Portraits (Box 29)
      - As a Young Girl, 1880s (Box 29, Folder 19-20)
      - With Siblings, 1880s-early 1890s (Box 29, Folder 21-22)
      - As a Young Woman, early 1890s (Box 29, Folder 23)
        Oversized material housed in Box 37
      - Portraits, early 1900s (Box 29, Folder 24)
      - Portraits, 1910s (Box 29, Folder 25)
      - Portraits by Baron Adolf de Meyer, 1910s (Box 29, Folder 26-27)
        Oversized material housed in Box 37 and OV 43
      - Portraits by Jean de Strelecki, 1916-1919 (Box 29, Folder 28)
      - Portraits, including portrait by Amemiya, circa 1919 (Box 29, Folder 29-30)
      - Portraits, 1920s-1930s (Box 29, Folder 31)
      - Proof Prints of Portraits by Edward Steichen, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 32)
      - Portraits, undated (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - In Costume, early 1900s (Box 29, Folder 34)
      Oversized materail housed in Box 37
    - With Harry Payne Whitney and Friends, 1915 (Box 29, Folder 35)
    - Hughes Campaign, 1916 (Box 29, Folder 36)
    - Traveling, 1920s (Box 29, Folder 37-38)
      Oversized material housed in OV 44-46
    - In Newport (with Charles Draper), 1920s (Box 29, Folder 39)
    - Receiving Honorary Degree from NYU, 1922 (Box 29, Folder 40)
    - With Flora Whitney, 1926 (Box 29, Folder 41)
    - With Dr. Boliario Porras (conferring about the Panama-Roosevelt Memorial?), 1927 (Box 29, Folder 42)
    - With Harry Payne Whitney at Belmont Park, 1928 (Box 29, Folder 43)
    - With Others, 1929 (Box 29, Folder 44)
    - In Florida (with friends), circa 1930s (Box 29, Folder 45)
    - At the Opening of the Whitney Museum of American Art, 1931 (Box 29, Folder 46)
    - At a Museum Luncheon, 1940 (Box 29, Folder 47)
    - At a Wedding with Flora Whitney Miller, 1941 (Box 29, Folder 48)
    - Reproductions of Portraits of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1880s-1920s (Box 29, Folder 49-50)
      Oversized material houesd in Box 37
    - Friends and Colleagues, 1909; undated (Box 29, Folder 51)
    - Suitors and Friends, circa 1918-1941 (Box 29, Folder 52)
    - Negatives, circa 1912-1915; undated (Box 29, Folder 53)
    - Oversize, Portraits, As a Young Woman scanned with Box 29, Folder 23, early 1890s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits scanned with Box 29, Folder 24, early 1900s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits scanned with Box 29, Folder 25, 1910s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits by Baron Adolf de Meyer scanned with Box 29, Folder 26, 1910s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits by Jean de Strelecki scanned with Box 29, Folder 28, 1916-1919 (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits, including Portrait by Amemiya scanned with Box 29, Folder 29, circa 1919 (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits scanned with Box 29, Folder 31, 1920s-1930s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, In Costume scanned with Box 29, Folder 24, early 1900s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, In Florida (with friends) scanned with Box 29, Folder 45, circa 1930s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Reproductions of Portraits of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney scanned with Box 29, Folder 49, 1880s-1920s (Box 37)
    - Oversize, Portraits by Baron Adolf de Meyer scanned with Box 29, Folder 26, 1910s (Box OV 43)
    - Oversize, Traveling scanned with Box 29, Folder 37, 1920s (Box OV 44-46)
  - Photographs of Residences and Studios, 1896-1935; 10.3
    This subseries consists of exterior and interior photographs of various residences belonging to the Whitney and Vanderbilt families, and photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's studios in Old Westbury, Long Island and at 34 Rue Jouvenet in Paris. Of particular note are photographs of the cottage, and its renovation, on the Whitney estate in Lenox, Massachusetts where Gertrude and Harry Payne Whitney spent part of their honeymoon in 1896.
    - Whitney and Vanderbilt Residences, undated (Box 29, Folder 54-56)
      Oversized material housed in OV 47
    - Interior, Residence at 871 Fifth Avenue, undated (Box 29, Folder 57)
    - Interiors, Unidentified, undated (Box 29, Folder 58)
      Oversized material housed in OV 48
    - House in Aiken, South Carolina, 1922; circa 1896 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Honeymoon Cottage, Whitney Estate in Lenox, Massachusetts, 1896 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Whitney Estate in Lenox, Massachusetts, undated (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - House in Westbury, Long Island, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Residence at 74 Park Avenue (snapshots), undated (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Residences, Unidentified (snapshots), 1935; 1927 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Studio in Old Westbury, undated (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Oversized material housed in OV 49
    - Studio in Paris (Box 30)
      - Loose Photographs, undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - Photograph Album, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - Scrapbook (unbound), "Studio, 34 Rue Jouvenet, Paris, France,", undated (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Oversize, Whitney and Vanderbilt Residences scanned with Box 29, Folder 56, undated (Box OV 47)
    - Oversize, Interiors, Unidentified scanned with Box 29, Folder 58, undated (Box OV 48)
    - Oversize, Studio in Old Westbury scanned with Box 30, Folder 7, undated (Box OV 49)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions, 1910s-1942; 10.4
    This subseries consists of photographs of various exhibitions and installations of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's sculpture, as well as photographs of exhibitions at the Whitney studio, such as the "Impressions of War" exhibition in 1919 and "The Circus in Paint" exhibition in 1929. Also found are photographs from the Memorial Show at the Whitney Museum of American Art held shortly after Whitney's death in 1942.
    Photographs in this subseries are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Exhibition, Whitney Studio, 1910s (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Oversized material housed in Box 38
    - Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Exhibitions, 1910s-1920s (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - "Impressions of the War" Exhibition, Scrapbook, 1919 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Installations, Paris Salon, 1920-1924 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - "The Circus in Paint" Exhibition, Whitney Studio Galleries, 1929 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - "Spirit of Flight" Installation, New York World's Fair, 1940 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Memorial Show at Whitney Museum of American Art, 1942 (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Oversize, Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Exhibition, Whitney Studio scanned with Box 30, Folder 11, 1910s (Box 38)
    - Oversize, Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Exhibitions scanned with Box 30, Folder 12, 1910s-1920s (Box 38)
    - Oversize, "Impressions of the War" Exhibition, Scrapbook scanned with Box 30, Folder 13, 1919 (Box 38)
    - Oversize, Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture Installations, Paris Salon scanned with Box 30, Folder 14, 1920-1924 (Box 38)
    - Oversize, "Spirit of Flight" Installation, New York World's Fair scanned with Box 30, Folder 16, 1940 (Box 38)
  - Photographs of Sculpture, 1904-1935; 10.5
    This subseries consists of photographs of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's sculptures. Extensive photographic documentation can be found for the Columbus Memorial and the St. Nazaire Memorial, including photographs related to planning, construction, and public unveiling. Photographs of Whitney posing with, working on, or attending the unveiling of her sculptures can be found amongst some of the files, including Buffalo Bill Memorial, Columbus Memorial, Fourth Division Memorial, St. Nazaire Memorial, Shepherd, Spirit of Flight, and Washington Heights War Memorial.
    Sculpture photographs are arranged in alphabetical order according to title. Photographs of various and unidentified sculptures and sculpture by others are arranged into files at the end of the subseries.
    - Arlington Fountain (McGill University, Montreal, Canada), 1931 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      Oversized material housed in Box 39 and OV 50
    - American Athlete (head), 1912 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Athlete (or Despair), 1912 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      Oversized material housed in Box 40
    - Aviator, 1918-1920 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Aviator with Propeller, undated (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Aztec Fountain (Pan-American Building, Washington, D.C.), 1910 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Blinded, undated (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Boy with Parrot and Dancer, undated (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - Bacchante, 1913 (Box 30, Folder 26)
    - Bailante, undated (Box 30, Folder 27)
    - Barbara, undated (Box 30, Folder 28)
    - Buffalo Bill Memorial (Cody, Wyoming), circa 1924 (Box 30, Folder 29-31)
    - Bunkies, 1920 (Box 30, Folder 32)
    - Caryatid, 1917 (Box 30, Folder 33)
    - Chateau Thierry, undated (Box 30, Folder 34)
    - Chinoise, 1914 (Box 30, Folder 35)
    - Colonel X, 1917 (Box 30, Folder 36)
    - Columbus Memorial (Port of Palos, Spain) (Box 30)
      - Early Sketches (not used), 1920s (Box 30, Folder 37)
      - Model and Drawing, 1928-1929 (Box 30, Folder 38-39)
      - Under Construction and Completed, 1920s (Box 30, Folder 40)
      - Unveiling, 1929 (Box 30, Folder 41-42)
    - D. A. R. Memorial, 1929 (Box 30, Folder 43)
    - Walter Damrosch (relief), 1922 (Box 30, Folder 44)
    - Dancing Girl and Pan, early 1920s (Box 30, Folder 45)
    - Daphne, 1933 (Box 30, Folder 46)
    - H. P. Davison Memorial, circa 1922 (Box 30, Folder 47)
    - Devotion, 1934 (Box 30, Folder 48)
    - El Dorado Fountain (Pan-Pacific International Exposition), 1910 (Box 30, Folder 49)
    - The Engineer, undated (Box 30, Folder 50)
    - Ferdinand and Isabella (Monument to Columbus), 1928-1929 (Box 30, Folder 51)
    - The Field Panel, 1904 (Box 30, Folder 52)
    - Found, 1920 (Box 30, Folder 53)
    - Fourth Division Memorial, 1921 (Box 30, Folder 54)
    - Fourth Division Memorial, Gertrude V. Whitney Working on Sculpture, 1921 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Gassed (or On the Top), undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - General Vanderbilt (head), 1935 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Captain Guardabassi, 1917 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Gwendolyn (head), 1934 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Home Again, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Honorably Discharged, undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - In the Trenches, 1918-1920 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Jo Davidson, 1917 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - John, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - John (head), 1935 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - The Kiss, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Last Charge, 1920 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - The Law (or Youth), 1922 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Charles Lindbergh Memorial, undated (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Mercy, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Monument to a Sculptor, 1910 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Mother and Child, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Nun, 1934 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Orders, 1918 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Paganism, 1907-1909 (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Pan, 1905 (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Pan, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Portrait of a Young Man, 1934 (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Private in the 15th Regiment, 1918-1920 (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Providence Memorial, undated (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Red Cross Nurse, 1918 (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - Refugee, undated (Box 31, Folder 28)
    - St. Nazaire Memorial (Box 31)
      - Model and Drawing, circa 1924 (Box 31, Folder 29)
      - Gertrude V. Whitney with Model, circa 1924 (Box 31, Folder 30)
      - Construction, circa 1924 (Box 31, Folder 31)
      - Unveiling, circa 1924 (Box 31, Folder 32)
      - Scrapbook, 1924 (Box 31, Folder 33)
    - Salome, 1936 (Box 31, Folder 34)
    - Shepherd, 1921 (Box 31, Folder 35)
    - Sighted, undated (Box 31, Folder 36)
    - Spirit of Flight, 1938-1939 (Box 31, Folder 37)
      Oversized material housed in Box 41
    - Spirit of Flight, Drawings, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 38)
    - Spirit of the Red Cross, 1920 (Box 31, Folder 39)
    - Springfield Memorial, circa 1929 (Box 31, Folder 40)
    - Spanish Peasant (head), 1911 (Box 31, Folder 41)
    - Peter Stuyvesant Statue, 1933 (Box 31, Folder 42)
    - Titanic Memorial, 1915 (Box 31, Folder 43)
    - Unemployed, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 44)
    - Untermeyer Memorial, Blumenthal Doors, circa 1915 (Box 31, Folder 45)
    - Victory Arch Panel, 1918-1920 (Box 31, Folder 46)
    - War Figure (sketch model), undated (Box 31, Folder 47)
    - Washington Heights War Memorial, 1924 (Box 31, Folder 48)
    - Washington Heights War Memorial, Unveiling, 1922 May 30 (Box 31, Folder 49)
    - Wherefore, 1910 (Box 31, Folder 50)
    - Various, Scrapbook, undated (Box 31, Folder 51)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 31, Folder 52)
    - Sculpture by Others, 1900s-1910s (Box 31, Folder 53)
    - Oversize, Arlington Fountain scanned with Box 30, Folder 18, 1931 (Box 39)
    - Oversize, Athlete (or Despair) scanned with Box 30, Folder 20, 1912 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Aztec Fountain scanned with Box 30, Folder 23, 1910 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Blinded scanned with Box 30, Folder 24, undated (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Boy with Parrot and Dancer scanned with Box 30, Folder 25, undated (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Chinoise scanned with Box 30, Folder 35, 1914 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Columbus Memorial, Model and Drawing scanned with Box 30, Folder 38, 1928-1929 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, D.A.R. Memorial scanned with Box 30, Folder 43, 1929 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Dancing Girl and Pan scanned with Box 30, Folder 45, early 1920s (Box 40)
    - Oversize, El Dorado Fountain scanned with Box 30, Folder 49, 1910 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Fourth Division Memorial, Gertrude V. Whitney Working on Sculpture scanned with Box 30, Folder 54, 1921 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Honorably Discharged scanned with Box 31, Folder 7, undated (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Last Charge scanned with Box 31, Folder 13, 1920 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Charles Lindbergh Memorial scanned with Box 31, Folder 15, undated (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Paganism scanned with Box 31, Folder 21, 1907-1909 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, St. Nazaire Memorial, Model and Drawing scanned with Box 31, Folder 29, circa 1924 (Box 40)
    - Oversize, Spirit of Flight scanned with Box 31, Folder 37, 1938-1939 (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Springfield Memorial scanned with Box 31, Folder 40, circa 1929 (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Titanic Memorial scanned with Box 31, Folder 43, 1915 (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Victory Arch Panel scanned with Box 31, Folder 46, 1918-1920 (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Wherefore scanned with Box 31, Folder 50, 1910 (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Sculpture by Others scanned with Box 31, Folder 53, 1900s-1910s (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Arlington Fountain, 1931 (Box OV 50)
  - Other Photographs, 1895-1915; 10.6
    This subseries consists of scattered, miscellaneous, and unidentified photographs. These include photographs of Charles Lindbergh (that may or may not relate to Whitney's planned, but never realized, memorial), the tomb of William C. Whitney, commerical scenic photographs, travel snapshots (with unidentified people), reproductions of various paintings and works of art by Robert Chanler, and photographs of other seemingly random or unidentified subjects.
    - Boats, undated; 1915 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Commercial Scenic Photographs, late 1800s? (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Charles Lindbergh, undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Oversized material housed in OV 51
    - Arthur H. Pollen (Photographer: Frederick Hollyer), 1895 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Polo, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Reproductions of Paintings, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Tomb of William C. Whitney, early 1900s (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Travel Snapshots (Box 32)
      - Venice and Europe, early 1900s (Box 32, Folder 9)
      - Adirondacks, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
      - Trip to West, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified, Snapshots, late 1800s? (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified, Portraits, late 1800s? (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Works of Art by Robert Chanler, undated (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Oversize, Works of Art by Robert Chanler scanned with Box 32, Folder 14, undated (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Miscellaneous scanned with Box 32, Folder 4, late 1800s-early 1900s (Box OV 51)
- Artwork, 1871-1930s; Series 11; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 32, 41, OVs 52-54
  This series consists of sketches created by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney and artwork by others collected by her.
  Artwork is arranged as two subseries.
  11.1: Sketches by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1891-1930s
  11.2: Artwork by Others, 1871-1916
  Artwork has been scanned in entirety.
  - Sketches by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1891-1930s; 11.1
    This subseries consists of sketchbooks and loose sketches by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, including early sketches done as a young girl, figure studies and anatomical drawings, sketches for and renderings of various sculptures, including the Titanic Memorial, Spirit of Flight, and St. Nazaire Memorial, and sketches of red cross nurses and soldiers grouped together under the head "My Experiences as an Emergency Canteen Worker."